בוקר טוב, Boker tov, חג שמח Chag sameach everybody. Happy יום העצמאות.
Yom Ha'atzmaut. I hope you all appreciate that I'm wearing blue and
white.
Anyway, let's start again. We start with this interesting משנה Mishna about
the making of these burial crypts. Let's read again from the
משנה Mishna itself on the bottom of ק' עמוד ב'. Kuf amud
bet. המוכר מקום לחברו לעשות לו קבר וכן המקבל מחברו לעשות לו
קבר. Hamocher makom lechavero la'asot lo kever vechen hamikabel michavero la'asot lo
kever. So you either sell a plot of land or a cave
for the purpose of using it as a family burial crypt or
you contract to construct it. So what are the presumed dimensions? עושה
תוכו של מערה ארבע אמות על שש. Oseh tocho shel me'arah arba
amot al shesh. The inside floor of the cave has to be
four by six. I guess it's telling you that it's a minimum
or if you have to excavate it.
ופותח לתוכה שמונה כוכין שלוש מכאן ושלוש מכאן ושניים מכנגדן. Ufotei-ach letocha
shmona kuchin shalosh mikan veshalosh mikan ushnayim miknegdan. So
therefore you've got this, it is four by six and whoops wrong
way, four by six and you're going to have, here's the door,
and you're going to have eight כוכין, kochin, eight niches. No, crypt
would be the right word there. Anyway כוך, kuch, eight niches. So
one, two, three, that's like divide by two in terms of the
number of אמות amot there are there, but the way it works
at least according to the
רשב"ם, Rashbam, six אמות amot you get three crypts. The way it
works is that each niche is an אמה, amah, each space between
them is an אמה. amah. So that's five. So that's almost divide
by two, there's one fewer space than there are crypts. I keep
on saying crypt, I don't know if that's the right word, anyway
niche, and then half an אמה amah at the
corners. The same would be true here, one, two, three and half
and a half is four. That's going to give you a total
of
eight.
Now the כוכין, kochin, and these actual niches, are אורכן ארבע אמות,
orkan arba amot, they're four אמות amot deep. So that's because that's
about six feet. That's going to be like the length, and now
again, I don't know if we have resolution on this, of whether
they would put the bodies in after they had decomposed or not,
but it is sounding from reading the תוספות Tosafot and the רשב"ם
Rashbam or whatever, that it's sounding like they put them in in
a coffin, and it sounds like maybe there's a skeleton there, but
nevertheless it seems like it was a coffin that once held the
body, so it sounds like we're dealing with the dimensions
of a recently dead body. Although again, from what I understand what
they would do is they would put a body on a shelf,
wait for it to decompose, and then put the bones in, but
then you would not need these dimensions, and תוספות Tosafot and the
רשב"ם Rashbam are discussing the dimensions of the human body. So I
don't know, we have to sort of figure that out.
But here you go. So it is ארבע אמות arba amot which
is six feet,
for Mediterranean people or whatever and Jews and so on that would
presumably be long enough, the body would be less than six feet.
So it is אורכן ארבע אמות ורומן שבעה. orkan arba amot veruman
shiva.
It would be שבעה טפחים shiva tefachim high, which is a little
more than an אמה, amah, 21 inches high. That's high enough for
the width of a body, not the width here, the thickness of
a body. ורוחבן שישה Verochban shisha
and the width here would be שישה טפחים shisha tefachim which is
like about 18 inches. As I was saying, I don't really fully
understand that because that means a person at their widest point is
18 inches and I don't know if that really works all the
time, but I guess there are also people that are sometimes wider,
taller than six feet, so I'm not exactly sure how those dimensions
suffice. Again, if we're dealing with that the body has decomposed, but
anyway, then you could obviously do what you want with the bones,
but maybe you just crunch it up a bit, but that seems
a little disrespectful. So I'm not exactly getting how those dimensions work.
רבי שמעון אומר, Rabbi Shimon omer, I mean that would be an
argument that a טפח tefach is more than three inches, but I
think that by now we assume that ר' חיים נאה Rabbi Chaim
Naeh was correct that they basically are three inches. So somebody can
do further research on exactly how those dimensions are big enough. But
that's the basic point. That's why these would be an אמה amah
wide is exactly this idea for the width of the coffin or
of the body you're putting in. רבי שמעון אומר Rabbi Shimon omer
עושה
תוכו של מערה שש
אמות.
Oseh tocho shel
me'arah shesh amot.
Now that's that four by six.
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says you make the inside שש אמות על
שמונה shesh amot al shmona six by eight, and ופותח לתוכה שלושה
עשר כוכין ufotei-ach letocha shlosha asar kuchin you get 13 in, ארבעה
מכאן וארבעה מכאן ושלושה מכנגדן ואחד מימין הפתח
ואחד משמאל. arba'ah mikan ve'arba'ah mikan ushlosha miknegdan ve'echad miyemin hapetach ve'echad
mismol. How would this work? So
basically, you can use the picture
there, so I'll just draw it right here with the dimensions, so
he says it would be six by eight. So again, we've got
it's basically divide by two. So this is going to be four
and that's going to be three. Okay, so one, two, three, four.
It's the same
basic spacing, okay, four here, three in between is seven, and half
and half, okay, right, is eight. Okay, so it's going to be,
so it's basically the same spacing except that he's just got it
to be bigger. So four, so that's eight, and three is eleven.
Okay, but he said thirteen. So what do you do with the
other two? So he says one on the left and one on
the right of the door, which makes it sound like he wants
you to put one here and one here, okay, which
is essentially longer.
What? Well, now this is like below ground. If you try to
draw, there's a whole little bit of a question about whether the
courtyard that people would be in would be at a higher than
the cave or not. It sounds like they would be. So if
you imagine here's the courtyard where the people carrying, you know, the
coffin are, okay, there they are carrying the coffin, okay, and then
they're going to go into, descend into like the cave here, okay,
or something of that nature. Alright, so if you're building something, it's
not exactly clear, like you know whatever, something like this. It's not
exactly clear. Anyway, if you're so if you're going to build it
in the wall here, right, I guess that would be the cave.
If you're going to build something, I don't know if you can
sort of fully, whatever, my picture isn't great. But anyway, but if
you can therefore get something in the wall of this cave and
this is the courtyard leading into the cave is higher than the
floor of it, so this would sort of be running under, you
know, under that surface. Is that somewhat clear how that would work?
I mean if you look at the picture here, right, you see
the picture the in the רשב״ם, Rashbam, the one that has like
four caves around a middle courtyard, right? So if you imagine the,
just imagine that the, you know, the floor of the courtyard is
not at the at the, you know, is sort of at the
top of the cave, not at the bottom of the cave. So
therefore, if you had the niche coming from the wall of the
opening outward, it would be running underneath the courtyard.
Alright, so that's sort of, yeah,
that's
sort of, I mean I guess
right, so here like, let's say it was like
this, and then you had it like that, again, and like the
opening of the cave was down here. Alright, so again, it's not
exactly clear how they would get into the opening of the cave,
but I kind of have a hard time drawing three dimensions here.
Anyway, but if it went under, it would go under like that,
okay, it would be under the base of the courtyard. That's what
it sounds like he's saying. But the גמרא's Gemara going to have
a hard time with that. Alright.
So, okay, now that's each individual cave. But it would be a
complex of caves, so it says ועושה חצר על פי המערה. ve-oso
chatzer al pi ha-me'ara. Now
you would have a courtyard by the opening of the cave. We're
going to see there'll be at least two and maybe four caves
per courtyard. ופתוח u-patoach שש על שש, shesh al shesh, six אמות
amot by six אמות, amot,
which would be basically nine feet by nine feet. Now the reason
for that, why is it six אמות amot by six אמות? amot?
Well, they're carrying here the dead body, the coffin. The coffin is
four אמות. amot. And they sort of got to like stand around
it, so you need a little more space than four אמות. amot.
So this courtyard would be six אמות amot by six אמות, amot,
okay, כמלא המטה וקובריה, ki-mlo ha-mitah ve-kovre'ha,
the length of the coffin and those who are burying it.
ופתוח לתוכו שתי מערות, u-patoach le-tocho shtei me'arot, אחת מכאן ואחת מכאן.
achat mikan ve-achat mikan.
So if you look at the first picture in the רשב״ם, Rashbam,
okay, that's a simple case, there would be two caves opening up
into a courtyard, fine, ואחת מכאן. ve-achat mikan. רבי שמעון אומר, ארבע
לארבע רוחותיה. Rabbi Shimon omer arba l'arba ruchoteiha, Now actually רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon really wants you to maximize, you know, the use of
the space here. Of course again, like, did the caves just conveniently
form themselves around a properly shaped courtyard? Like you got to wonder,
like what are we talking about? Like obviously it seems to be
like maybe a whole major construction would have to be done in
order to make this happen. So I'm not exactly sort of getting,
you know...
We'll do a field trip to בית שערים. Beit She'arim.
Excellent, excellent. Let's find somebody who's going to sponsor that.
But then you can see several of these.
I know, I know, I tried, so I looked up on like
Wikipedia, I searched looked up on Google. The problem is they always
just show you the facade, cause the facade is the most impressive,
and they never like, I'm looking for like a floor scheme, you
know, so I can match it up against this, but I'm having
a hard time finding it. Maybe there's some good archaeological books you
know of or whatever. I would I would really like to try
to match it up with what we know.
From memory it was like a courtyard that you walk into the
different מערות. me'arot.
And it was like this? Yeah. and that there were caves around
it or, I don't, I mean, if you have a—look, if you've
got a natural cave, you know,
if you have a natural cave then you have a court you
make a courtyard in front of the natural cave. If you happen
to have a few caves, but you're never going to exactly—to make
something exactly this scheme, how do you do that on naturally occurring
thing?
No, that's why he's a contractor, he has to like dig it
out or something.
I guess, I mean, I guess if the whole thing is a
huge cave, you collapse the cave in the middle, you turn part
of that into a courtyard. I don't—anyway, I'm having a hard time
totally figuring it out. Okay, רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon אומר omer, ארבע
לארבע רוחותיה, arba le-arba ruchote'ha. רבן שמעון בן גמליאל אומר הכל לפי
הסלע. Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel omer hakol lefi hasela. So, oh, I
right,
you've—significantly somebody says look, you gotta figure out what type of rock
you're dealing with. Now, does that mean that that determines how many
caves you have? Does that mean that determines how many niches you
have in each cave? Right, but anyway, the רשב"ם Rashbam has a
couple of possible explanations. But at least he's saying like you can't
just give this. But part—partly, look, it's also a niche of a
contractor. So before you get to the whole complex, you know, you
Michael have hired me to dig out the cave and I made
my eleven niches or whatever however many niches I made. I made
my eight niches, and you say to me, "Hey Dov, you know,
the wall there is strong enough, sturdy enough, it can support a
couple more niches." Or I only made six, and you say, "Hey,
you're supposed to do eight." And I say, "No, the wall isn't
sturdy enough for eight, it'll only support six." Which makes a lot
of sense, but then who's to determine any of those disputes? Right,
who do you get that—that sort of—that judges those cases when we're
debating what what I should have done? So, yes.
I'm sensing הרב סמט, HaRav Samet, but just to support our field
trip we've also בית בד beit bad on site.
Oh, good, so we can do from earlier discussions too. Excellent.
So, although I know this isn't being addressed here, I guess this
is the same conversation we had earlier if you get a right
of access to this because it doesn't say anything
about—oh yeah, that's a good point too. I mean, the גמרא Gemara
earlier did say דרך הקבר, derech hakever, so it sounds like you
have to explicitly buy דרך הקבר. derech hakever. Yeah, that was discussed
earlier. Okay, so now let's take a look.
This משנה mishnah is in conversation with that other גמרא. Gemara. Yeah,
yeah, we don't—we don't know,
but—yeah, but the other one did already relate to the דרך הקבר
derech hakever and the מקום מעמד makom ma’amad and the הספד, hesped,
so these are all—you're right, they're sort of in the same conversation.
Okay, so let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. הני תרי
להיכא שדי להו? Hanei terei l’heicha shadi lehu? So one's asking, according
to רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, these two, where are you placing them?
Okay? Because again, it sounds like maybe this—this is too complicated there,
but this is where the courtyard is, so and these are underneath
the courtyard. It sounds like they're going in the wall of the
opening and underneath the courtyard. So it says like this: אי לבראי,
Ei lebarai, if they're outwards, outside of the cave and under the
courtyard,
הא קמי דיישי להו. haka midashi lehu. First of all, they're—they're trampled,
means if you're constantly walking, there's a lot of traffic in the
courtyard, maybe people would gather there for a eulogy beforehand, you'd wait
till everybody gathered, you'd whatever, there'd be a lot of walking, so
it's assuming that that's not going to be good for the ceiling
above it and going to maybe cause, you know, cause it to—to
collapse or something. I don't know, like sometimes walking is how good
it compresses stuff. But the גמרא Gemara thinks it's not—if you're doing
it directly under this ground and this ground is heavily traveled, that's
not going to be safe, number one. Number two, ותו, v’tu, which
is probably the better question, התנן חצר הקבר העומד בתוכו טהור. hatnan
chatzar hakever ha’omed betocho tahor. If you're standing here in this courtyard,
you're טהור tahor because all of the graves are, you know, off
into the caves outside of the courtyard, so being in the courtyard
itself, there's no טומאה tumah that hits you, even like if טומאה
tumah were to come out of the cave or whatever, there's no
roof over the courtyard to carry the טומאה. tumah. Right, everybody sort
of understand how that operates? Here I am, I'm standing here, there's
all these graves in all four directions, you know, even if the
caves open up, if we're not under a similar roof, I'm טהור.
tahor. But the problem is, but if there're graves directly beneath me,
then I'm not, and the טומאה tumah goes up. So how could
I be טהור tahor standing in the courtyard? Okay? העומד בתוכו טהור.
Ha’omed betocho tahor. So clearly these are not being dug under the
courtyard. So אמר רבי יוסי ברבי חנינא דעביד להו כמין נגר. Amar
Rabbi Yosei b’Rabbi Chanina de’avid lehu kemin nagar. You make it like
a doorbolt, okay, a vertical doorbolt. So what the גמרא Gemara seems
to be saying
is—is that you basically, yes, you do do it at the opening,
which is what the משנה mishnah sounds like, but you do it
sort of like straight into the wall here. Okay? I mean again,
I'm sort of—I'm trying to do a different dimension. Yeah. They're—you bury
people standing. You can do that? So the גמרא’s Gemara going to
say, since when are you allowed to bury somebody standing?
Okay, we haven't got to that
answer, but but if you bury them standing in the wall, I'm
trying to think if I can sort of draw a picture. So
these are like coming out into like that way, okay, and if
this is the opening here, and these are sort of buried like,
you know, vertically standing into the wall. Seems very bizarre, right, to
walk through an opening and have two like things buried into the
wall like directly parallel.
I've been
in Rome like that, have they?
I—I was there once and at least my memory is that it
was horizontal, but I don't remember, yeah.
And I thought what they did was they laid the body out
on a shelf.
Yeah, so I mentioned that I think before you came in,
and they're—it's one above the other.
Right, right, I—yeah, exactly. So that is also my understanding and everything.
Again, from all of these discussions, it sounds like we're talking about
the whole body in its shape in a coffin. So, no, no,
no, I agree with you because everything I've read seems like they
would wait for it to decompose. Now the גמרא Gemara talks about
a thing, a year after it was buried, called ליקוט עצמות, Likut
Atzamot, which basically would be that, the gathering of the bones, and
it actually sounds exactly like that. Maybe you would bury in a
ground. By the way, apparently from elsewhere everything I read, and I
said this before, this sounds like only the very wealthy did this,
otherwise people were buried in the ground. But it was a burial
in a ground, you'd wait till the body decomposed, you'd take the
bones, okay, and then you would put them into the wall here.
But other things I read indicated that actually it was, they were
left on a shelf in this space and then it was just
put. But all of this doesn't sound that way because all of
this deals with the normal dimensions of a person and of a
coffin. And we're going to see in a minute, the גמרא Gemara
is going to object to this idea, because it says you can't
bury a person standing up. Right? If it were bones, like, you
know, you could just compact them or whatever. So the גמרא Gemara
sounds like we're dealing with the actual burial of the whole body
in its shape. Okay, but yeah, I don't understand how that corresponds
to what we know about this. So the גמרא Gemara says, ואמר
רבי יוחנן, V'amar Rabbi Yochanan, for Rabbi Yochanan says, קבורת חמורים היא
זו. Kevurat Chamorim hi zo.
This is like how you would bury a donkey. This isn't how
you treat a human body. You don't bury like, you know, you
don't bury a human body standing up. Now the רשב"ם Rashbam says
why does it mean donkey? Says שמשיליכים בבור. shemashlichim b'vor. So I
don't know again, if I hope it's a בור bor that's not
being used for a water supply, but anyway, like he said, but
if you throw somebody down a well or a body, you know,
a donkey, it's more or less standing up, you don't lay it
out. Also donkey, anyway, whatever. So, but a human being you lay
down, so you don't, you know, you know itself of the just
the euphemisms we use, like to, you know, like
you will lay with your fathers,
ושכבת עם אבותיך, v'shachavta im avotecha, right, so, ושכבתי עם אבותי, v'shachavti
im avotei, right, thank you, ושכבתי עם אבותי, v'shachavti im avotei, right.
So, you know, anyway, it's not considered to be respectful to the
human.
So, so Rabbi Yochanan, so obviously, so what are you going to
do? It says, okay, fine, for Rabbi Yochanan, so it's interesting the
way it responds, for Rabbi Yochanan. It sounds like maybe not everybody
agrees with Rabbi Yochanan. But for that opinion, that it's not appropriate
to bury somebody standing up, דעביד להו בקרן זוית. D'avid lehu b'keren
zavit. You do it in the corner. Now what does the corner
mean here? There's a whole long רשב"ם Rashbam and תוספות. Tosafot. We're
just going to deal with the easiest explanation, which was the picture
that you saw on the first slide, which is that you do
it here. Okay?
So that's where you do it. So when it says one to
the right and one to the left, it doesn't mean on the
wall of the doorway, but if you're entering in the doorway, you
know, on the opposite wall, there's another one to the right and
to the left. Okay, so that's what it means בקרן זוית. b'keren
zavit.
Is there an order which you're supposed to fill these things in?
No, that's I... that's an interesting question. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara
says, one minute, והא נוגעי כוכין להדדי. v'ha nogei kukin l'hadadi. One
minute, says the גמרא, Gemara, then this, these things will intersect. Why
will they intersect? Because as you remember, I said that there was
a half אמה amah here. This is the way the רשב"ם Rashbam
understands, and a half אמה amah here. Okay, which means that the
diagonal, the גמרא Gemara assumes that a 1.4 right, that a 1
by
has a diagonal is square root of 2, 1.4 is actually pretty
close, 1.414 etc. That's what the גמרא Gemara assumes, a diagonal of,
you know, a 1 by 1 right-angle triangle is 1.4. So if
this is here a half by a half, what's this diagonal? So
0.5 times 1.4 is 0.7. So this opening here is not an
אמה. amah. If you were to dig straight into this wall you'd
have 0.7 of an אמה. amah. But, if people are with me
here why that's true, but the width of the כוך kuch has
to be an אמה. amah. So you're going to have to, if
you want to get it to be a full אמה, amah, cut
into the openings of these, right? So here we'll do it a
lot closer so you see more why it's a problem visually. Okay?
So 0.7 even if I cut away this corner it's not big
enough, so I'm gonna have to do like that in order to
get me my full אמה. amah. And the גמרא Gemara feels like
that's obviously totally inappropriate, besides which maybe won't fit, okay, but you
don't cut... you have to keep each one distinct. So that's not
going to work, says the גמרא. Gemara. So the גמרא Gemara says,
והא נוגעי כוכין להדדי. v'ha nogei kukin l'hadadi. אמר רב אשי Amar
Rav Ashi במעמיק. b'mamek. Okay,
who says you do it at the same height? Who says you
do it at the same plane? You make this diagonal one a
little lower or a little higher, right? You know, so therefore it...
the opening can be totally wide enough. It's just if all the
other openings, if this opening is here and this opening is here,
this one is like down here or up here, so it doesn't
have to intersect, right, with these others. All right?
Maybe you just don't space those last ones on the corner of
an אמה.
amah. Right. Well, another way to have said it would have been
why don't you just say that you have less than an אמה
amah here, give yourself some more space. I don't know why the
גמרא Gemara didn't say that. That's completely correct, the גמרא Gemara because
the משנה Mishnah never tells you exactly what the spacing is between
this. But anyway, but the point here is that you don't have...
have to have them all on the same plane. If you do
one, if you do this a diagonal one higher or lower, then
it could be fine. Of course that raises the question which רשב"ם
Rashbam tells us then you could do more niches all around. You
could just have multiple layers. And I think that there are ossuaries
that exactly have that, that have multiple layers. But what they say
is well maybe that won't be good for the structure of the
wall to have multiple holes going along the same wall and so
on, you need the stability of the wall. But here when you
dig this out in this direction, if you had multiple things going
at different layers here, they'd all be cavities all lined up or
all, whatever in the same plane, but this is going away from
the other cavities. So here it's more structurally
sound to do that and with doing it at a different layer.
But doing in the same wall different layers, you could make it,
you could do it, but it would not be as structurally sound.
That's at least what the רשב"ם Rashbam and תוספות Tosafot say. Okay,
everybody sort of get the answer here? Yeah, okay fine. So it
says, okay, אילימא תימא הכי, Ilima teima hachi, ארבע עשרה כוכין היכי
עביד להו, arba asara kuchin heichi avid lehu, הא קא נגחו כוכי
להדדי. ha ka nagchu kuchei lehadadi.
It says yeah because besides which, I was waiting for somebody to
ask this, right, according to רבי שמעון Rebbe Shimon that you've got
your erase this for now that you've got your four מערות mearot
opening up into your courtyard, okay, so you've got your four מערות
mearot opening up into your courtyard. We got a problem. What's the
problem you've got? That, no, well the entrance isn't that good of
a- that's fine. But here,
that's ארבע אמות, arba amot, ארבע אמות, arba amot, right, ארבע אמות,
arba amot, ארבע אמות, arba amot, there's going to be a lot
of overlap if you think about it, right, because anyway, so what's
going to- how is it that they're not going to- they're not
going to intersect? So it must be that perpendicular caves, they make
it at different heights, right. So the גמרא Gemara says, אלא במעמיק,
ela be-ma'amik, so it must be that some are lower and some
are higher. הכא נמי במעמיק, hacha nami be-ma'amik, here too he would
do the same thing for the ones in the diagonal corners. Alright,
now we have a more- a more ingenious answer, which the גמרא
Gemara is not going to like, but it's so ingenious. ורב הונא
בריה דרב יהושע אמר ארבע מערות לרבי שמעון דעביד להו כי חרוזא.
Ve-Rav Huna breih de-Rav Yehoshua amar arba mearot le-Rabbi Shimon de-avid lehu
ki charuza.
I'm going to tell you how you're going to solve this problem
without saying it has to be at different levels. It's going to
be like a palm branch that has, I don't know if you've
ever seen a לולב, lulav, once it starts spreading out, they're like,
they're like all- they're like these diagonals. So he says that's what
you're going to do here. You're going to, okay, everything at an
angle. You're going to dig them at an angle,
and then you're going to do this at an angle.
So that's how you're going to avoid them intersecting. You're going to
have everything at an angle, so it looks like the side of
a palm branch. That sounds like a nice answer. Okay, you have
a little picture here in the רשב"ם, Rashbam, the last picture in
the רשב"ם. Rashbam. Okay, דעביד להו כי חרוזא. de-avid lehu ki charuza.
So the גמרא Gemara says, והא דרב הונא בריה דרב
יהושע בדותא היא. ve-ha de-Rav Huna breih de-Rav Yehoshua baduta hi. But
that's, or something, בדותא, baduta, that's a joke, that's false, that's wrong.
That doesn't make any sense. Why? מכדי, michdei, let's take a look.
כל אמתא בריבועא אמתא ותרי חומשי באלכסונא. kol amta be-ribu'a amta ve-trei
chumshai be-alchasona. כל אמתא בריבועא, kol amta be-ribu'a,
any אמה amah by an אמה amah square so again this is
looking at two perpendicular lines, an אמה amah by an אמה amah
so אמתא ותרי חומשי amta ve-trei chumshai is 1.4, an אמה amah
and two-fifths, 1.4 באלכסונא be-alchasona in the diagonal. Okay, so that's the
square root of two is 1.4.
Anything that is one by one, that's אמתא בריבועא amta be-ribu'a is
1.4 in the diagonal.
Okay, so anyway, now why is that relevant? So כמה הוו להו,
kama havu lehu, חד סרי וחומשא. chad sari ve-chumsha. So how much
therefore is the diagonal here?
11.2.
What does that mean? It means that this diagonal now why do
we care about this diagonal? We can try to figure it out
in a minute, but this diagonal, how long is this diagonal? Well
this is eight, this is eight, so eight times 1.4 is eight,
3.2 is 11.2. Okay, you can do the math and check it,
it's correct. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says this horizontal is 11-
this diagonal is 11.2.
Now,
כוכין כמה הוו, kuchin kama havu, תמניא. tamnya. So how many crypts
are there here? Eight. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says and niches,
I missed a few, I only have three, I gotta get four,
whatever. Okay, eight. So the גמרא Gemara says, so תמניא tamnya says
the גמרא, Gemara, בחד סרי וחומשא היכי
משכחת לה. be-chad sari ve-chumsha heichi mashkachat lah.
So the גמרא's Gemara going to say if you imagine it, all
of these כוכין kuchin whether they actually do cross the diagonal line
or not, at least virtually have to, in terms of the space
they're taking up, they
virtually imagine them continuing on, right? So imagine everything has to eventually
cross this diagonal line, even if it doesn't get up to it,
I imagine these don't get up to it, I haven't done the
math, but at least conceptually the amount of space it's taking up,
you would imagine you could continue it on and it would cross
that line. So if everything is crossing that line, right, then says
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, then one minute, then this line here which
is 11.2, right, so if you think about it, it's got to
have here an אמה amah *amah* for the krip that crosses here
and here's an אמה amah. *amah* here and here's an אמה amah.
*amah* here, so there's going to be eight אמות amahs, *amos* for
the places where all the krips cross, okay, and then you're only
left with 3.2.
So 3.2 is not enough spacing to exist between
eight krips
if you're assuming you have to have an אמה amah *amah* space,
right? Maybe, correct. Okay, so that would be a possibility. But that's
how the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says if you think about it, the
area taken up when these cross the imaginary diagonal is going to
be eight אמות amahs *amos* for the eight krips, so you're not
going to have, you're only left with 3.2, that's not enough to
space between them. Now, I haven't totally figured this out, but to
me, I don't exactly get why it's a problem because because here
at the corner, right, and I'm not sure... it's pulling more on
the other side... well here at the corner, since when does it
have to take up a whole אמה *amah* at the corner, right,
you know, if it's basically like this, I don't know, I haven't
figured it out, but it seems to me like it's not going
to take up a whole אמה *amah* at the corner because it's
mostly going out. Somebody could sort of go ahead and you know
do the geometry and figure that out. But the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
says it's not going to fit. Now an easier way, right, an
easier way to have made the argument, which he'd make it a
קושיא *kushya*, now
an easier way to have made the argument would have been to
say, and maybe this is the real point of the גמרא *Gemara*,
is to say when you cut it out here, you're not cutting
out an אמה *amah*, you cut out an אמה *amah* if you
were doing it perpendicularly. If the width is an אמה *amah* and
you're cutting it out at an angle, okay, so if the width
here is an אמה *amah*, I think what it's saying is if
that's an אמה *amah*, right, that's the width, right, then the cut
you have to make there because it's at an angle is going
to have to be more than an אמה *amah* and it might
actually be the 1.4. I haven't exactly... but you sort of you
see that, right? If that is an אמה *amah* wide and here's
your wall, okay, and but the actual thing is an אמה *amah*
wide, but you're cutting it into the wall at an angle, okay,
it looks to me like the cut is going to be the
1.4 אמות amahs *amos*. And that really might have been the point
of the גמרא *Gemara*, okay, which is that it's going... that you're
going actually the cut in the walls are going to have to
be significantly, you know, more than an אמה *amah* and therefore you're
not going to have enough wall space to cut those out. People
sort of get the point there? Alright, so that's the point of
the גמרא *Gemara*, they says that won't work. There's a brilliant answer,
but it won't work, there's not enough wall space to make that
happen. Alright, so the גמרא *Gemara* says,
okay, אלא הדר רב הונא בריה דרב יהושע פרוסה היא *ella hadar
Rav Huna brei d'Rav Yehoshua pruse hi*, so therefore it's rejected, it's
false. Okay, ואיבעית אימא *v'iba'it eima*, so that's one answer. One answer
is how do we deal with, you know, these type of... how
do we deal with these two things here if they're too big,
like the cutaway at the diagonal would cut into these other krips?
So one answer is they're at different heights. ואיבעית אימא *v'iba'it eima*,
if you want I'll give you another explanation of how you sort
of can deal with these things and they are, ואיבעית אימא *v'iba'it
eima* כדאמר רב ששת בריה דרב אידי בנפילי הכא נמי בנפילי *kidamar
Rav Sheshet brei d'Rav Idi binpili hacha nami binpili*. בנפילי *binpili*, so
we're dealing with fetuses, so miscarriages, alright, which is actually interesting, right,
because
there's not really a מצוה *mitzvah* of burying a baby who was
a miscarriage, but presumably they would do it unless נפילי *nefili* also
means like an infant birth or something, but a very small, you
know, very small baby. So חס ושלום *chas v'shalom*, so in those
cases it says you don't need a full אמה *amah*, so you
could sort of fit it in here in less than an אמה
*amah* and that's why it would work in this corner. Might actually
be why it would work actually here at this opening, right? Because
now you don't need to go four אמות amot *amos* down and
you don't need to do it perpendicular, maybe it's a way we
could say that you do do it right in the wall at
the opening, but if you're talking about a very small child, you
know, a baby, so you know that's a way of explaining that.
So that's another way of dealing with the question we have, which
is where do those two extra go? It also might be the
way what the גמרא *Gemara* is saying is of dealing with the
problem here of how these intersect. And that's it's saying that at
those intersection points you use those for babies. Now the point is
though, if you do the math, these really are all three of
these are going to intersect, right? Because think about it. Let's sort
of do this, right? have one,
two, how far do we have here? That's one אמה, two אמות,
amot three, three and a half so when you're even with within
four אמות amos you're already starting the third thing. And these things
go four אמות amos? high. So the first three of them are
going to intersect, okay, three out of four. There's going to be
a lot of intersection. So if we're using, people understand that, right?
So if we're using, there's only four along each wall. And at
the corners, three are going to intersect. So if we're using this
for for infants,
okay, that means that three, and you want to use it to
prevent the intersection, okay, that means that three out of each cave
of, each cave has how many, four, three, four, 13, right? This
is for רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, three out of 13 are going
to be used for infants. Which I don't know, I haven't looked
at the statistics, but in the ancient world that probably makes a
lot of sense. There's a lot of infant death. Okay, so that's
actually interesting if that's the answer to the intersection here, not just
to the extra two, then you actually have for every cave of
13 of these niches,
three out of 13. What is that? That's probably what about 20%
or something.
It's one or two cubits long.
Okay, so yeah. So anyway, that's so that's a very high number
there. But again, it makes sense from what we know about the
ancient world. All right. So now the גמרא continues. תנן התם. Tnan
hatam. So now we're done with the geometry. Take a breath. Okay,
so now we get to a more straight הלכה halacha discussion. I'll
just read a little bit. We don't want to get too far
ahead. We're already a דף daf ahead. Okay, we'll just get started.
המוציא מת מושכב כדרכו, Hamotzi met mushkav kedarko, נוטל לו ואת תפוסתו.
notel lo ve'et tfusato.
So you're going ahead and you're digging in
your in your wheat field and you're planting or whatever, and there
you as you're digging, you find that there's a dead body. In
Israel, anytime anybody wants to do a construction and they start like
digging up the ground to lay the foundation, they have to call
the Department of Antiquities because they've found some something of archaeological significance.
So here, it seems like you would start digging and you'd find
a dead body. So the question is like this. You have
to so what do you do? So you're allowed to actually redig
it up and reinter it, disinter and reinter it in a cemetery,
and sort of take it out of your yard. You don't want
to have a dead body underneath and your whole field become טמא
tamei and whatever. Obviously, you move it to a cemetery. Okay, so
נוטל לו ואת תפוסתו. notel lo ve'et tfusato. You take it and
you take the תפוסה, tfusa, like the word לתפוס litfos is to
grab. It means sort of the dirt that's directly underneath it because
you're afraid that some of
the body, the the liquids or whatever from the body have seeped
into the ground underneath it. So you take some of the ground
underneath it. There's a discussion of how much and you basically and
you reinter it somewhere else. Now, שנים נוטלם ואת תפוסתן. shnayim notlam
ve'et tfusatan. If two bodies, same thing. You still assume that it
was some random reason that some bodies were buried here. By the
way, the reason it says מושכב כדרכו, mushkav kedarko, lying in the
natural way, was because if it was found in an unnatural position,
standing up, folded over and so on, then you're certainly going to
assume that this was not naturally buried, this was some was a
murder victim or whatever it might have been. The reason this is
relevant is because when you find three, and all three of them
were buried in a natural way, then you say, it looks like
we got a cemetery here, not just one or two dead bodies.
Okay, that's the next line. מצא שלושה, matza shlosha, now you've found
three. אם יש ביניהם מארבע ועד שמונה, im yesh beinehem me'arba ve'ad
shmona, הרי זה שכונת קברות. harei ze shchunat kvarot. If you have
between four אמות amos, and eight אמות amos between them, you have
here a neighborhood of graves, okay, you have here presumably what was
a cemetery. And therefore the הלכה halacha is that then you're not
allowed to disinter it. Then you actually have to leave them. You
could disinter and reinter if you say this really doesn't belong here,
it must have been buried as an emergency measure. We're now going
ahead and rebury it. But if this is where they were buried,
okay, buddy, you got a cemetery underneath your wheat field. You can't
destroy that. You have to leave it. And now you have to
check the area around to make sure
where might there be other bodies so that if any כהן kohen
or anybody comes through, they know how far is the extent of
the cemetery. So ובודק הימנו ולהלן עשרים אמה. uvodek himenu ulehalan esrim
amah. You check like in all directions 20 אמה from these bodies
to see if there are any other bodies. מצא אחד בסוף עשרים
אמה, matza echad besof esrim amah, so in one direction you found
one body at the end of 20 אמה. Okay, but now that
proves that the cemetery went at least that far. And now you
have to keep on checking from that body another
אמה. בודק הימנו ולהלן עשרים אמה. bodek himenu ulehalan esrim amah. שרגלים
לדבר, she'raglayim ladavar, that now there
is the matter has legs, we say there's
substantial. evidence that we're dealing with a real cemetery once you have
three. שאילו מתחילה מצאו נוטלו
ואת תפוסתו. she-ilu mitchila matzu notlo ve-es tfusaso. So if you had
just found the one body there, 20 אמות amos away, you would
have disinterred it and reinterred it. But now that you're finding it
in the context of exploring the area around these three bodies, you
don't assume it's a single body, you assume it's part of this
cemetery, and therefore you're going to keep on checking. Okay. Now so
that's the ברייתא, braisa, we will unpack that tomorrow, ending a little
early today. But the interesting thing is is that, again, I don't
know how this fits with what we know, but if you're digging
in your ground, you're presumably not digging up a cave underneath your
ground. Presumably we're talking about soil and we're talking about a normal
type of a burial in soil, which as I said from what
we know was the way most people were buried. But the גמרא
is going to read this through the lens of our discussion and
assuming that those graves that you are digging into and finding are
graves from one of these caves underneath. I mean I imagine if
you were hitting into the wall of a cave, you would probably
realize it, again I don't know enough about that. But anyway, but
that's what we're going to assume and therefore it's going to focus
on these dimensions. Why do we go 20 אמות? amos Why do
we say between four and eight? But between four, by the way,
just to show you, easy to understand because if this is one
and one and one and this is one אמה here, so if
you found three graves, okay, and they are so three graves within
four אמות, amos right, so that's three, one two three, one two
three four, and the other one starts I guess just within four
אמות amos or maybe it's here because there's a half, you know,
you found three here, mostly three graves will be close to like
four אמות amos within four אמות of one another. Why they would
be within eight אמות of one another might be because you might
be finding two graves here and one grave there. You know, so
there's sort of a bigger gap between them. So the גמרא is
going to read this issue, not just about graves burial in the
ground, but as if what you discovered were the niches here that
were buried like in the wall of a cave, and like your
ground is above the cave. Yes.
If you found three bodies that was buried today, someone that you
should know, right, and you dug 20 אמות around and found nothing,
right, would you still consider that a cemetery?
Well you couldn't disinter those bodies, you would have to leave them
there.
And anything you do you'd have to go within 20 אמות beyond?
No, you would be allowed to bury, you know, you could do
stuff like on top, I mean, I mean the basic point would
be a טומאה tumah point. You'd have to have like markers, which
is like, you know, there are bodies buried under this space or
whatever. The basic point is is that you can't disinter and you
have to now this area of your ground you have to know
is above graves and there's a טומאה tumah issue. That's the basic
concern.
Does it plant something?
Yeah, I mean, yeah, it seems like that's not, that sounds disrespectful,
you know, but you can't.
What? Can you pick whatever you plant on top? Like that's the
question.
Yeah, well there's no, what do you mean like איסור הנאה? issur
hana'ah?
That's only from the body, but there's the טומאה. tumah. Well, if
you're not a כהן, kohen, I mean, if you're you just have
to assume that everything is טמא, tamei, you know. I mean you're
allowed if you're ישראל Yisrael and not a כהן kohen or whatever
you're allowed to do have טומאה tumah going around. But yeah, it's
an interesting question about respect because, you know, a lot of these
cases here about these caves, you know, you'd be walking what I
didn't discuss is the way you get to the courtyard was you'd
be walking over the caves, you know, on the ground over the
caves and then come down into the courtyard. So you could regularly
walk above graves knowing there are graves like it's not like now,
like actually the grave is close to the surface and you have
a gravestone. Obviously, you know, that's one, you know, you don't start
סתם stam walking cutting, you know, walking on top of graves that
way. But if they're deep in the ground, you know, it seems
like yeah they would do that.
So the primary concern here is not about the use of the
space, it's about like that there's you have to leave the bodies
there and know that there's טומאה tumah underneath. Okay. But we will
continue with all of this tomorrow.
Okay, חג שמח Chag sameach everybody.